CHAPTER 17 A week later Dorian Gray was sitting in the conservatory at Selby Royal,
talking to the pretty Duchess of Monmouth, who with her husband, a jaded
looking man of 60 was amongst his guests. It was tea time and the mellow
light of the huge lace covered lamp that stood on the table lit up the delicate
china and hammered silver of the service at which the duchess was presiding ing
Her white hands were moving daintily among the cups, and her full red lips
were smiling at something that Dorian had whispered to her. Lord Henry was
lying back in a silk draped wicker chair, looking at them. On a peach colored divan
sat Lady nabbar pretending to listen to the duke’s description of the last
Brazilian beetle that he had added to his collection. Three young men in elaborate
smoking suits were handing teacakes to some of the women. The house party
consisted of 12 people, and there were more expected to arrive on the next
day what What are you two talking about?” said Lord Henry, strolling over to the
table and putting his cup down. “I hope Dorian has told you about my plan for
rechristening everything Gladis It is a delightful idea.” “But I don’t want to be
Rec christened Harry,” rejoined the duchess, looking up at him with her
wonderful eyes I'm quite satisfied with my own name, and I'm sure Mr. Gray should
be satisfied with his.” “My dear Gladis I would not alter
either name for the world. They are both perfect. I was thinking chiefly of
flowers. Yesterday I cut an orchid, for my button hole It was a marvelous spotted
thing, as effective as the seven deadly sins. In a thoughtless moment I asked one
of the gardeners what it was called. He told me it was a fine specimen of Robin
sonana or something dreadful of that kind. It is a sad truth, but we have lost
the faculty of giving lovely names to things. Names are everything. I never
quarrel with actions. My one quarrel is with words. That is the reason I hate
vulgar realism in literature. The man who could call a spade a spade should be
compelled to use one. It is the only thing he is fit for.” “Then what should we
call you, Harry?” she asked. “His name is Prince Paradox,” said Dorian. “I recognize
him in a flash,” exclaimed the duchess. “I won’t hear of it,” laughed Lord
Henry, sinking into a chair. “From a label there is no escape! I refuse the
title.” “Royalties may not abdicate,” fell as a warning from pretty
lips. “You wish me to defend my throne, then?” “Yes.” “I give the truths of
tomorrow I prefer the mistakes of today she answered. “You disarm me gladice he
cried, catching the willfulness of her mood. “Of your shield, Harry, not of your
spear.” “I never tilt against beauty,” he said, with a wave of his hand. “That is
your error, Harry, believe me. You value beauty far too much.” “How can you say that?
I admit that I think that it is better to be beautiful than to be good. But on
the other hand, no one is more ready than I am to acknowledge that it is better to
be good than to be ugly.” “Ugliness is one of the seven deadly sins, then?” cried the
duchess. “What becomes of your simile about the orchid?” “Ugliness is one of the seven
deadly virtues Gladis You, as a good Tory, must not underrate them. Beer, the Bible,
and the seven deadly virtues have made our England what she
is.” “You don’t like your country, then?” she asked. “I live in it.” “That you may censure
it the better.” “Would you have me take the verdict of Europe on it?” he inquired.
“What do they say of us?” “That tartu has immigrated to England and opened a shop.”
“Is that yours, Harry?” “I give it to you.” “I
could not use it. It is too true.” “You need not be afraid. Our countrymen never
recognize a description.” “They are practical.” “They are more cunning than
practical. When they make up their ledger, they balance stupidity by wealth, and
vice by hypocrisy.” “Still, we have done great things.” “Great things have been thrust on
us gladice We have carried their burden.” “Only as far as the Stock Exchange.” She
shook her head. “I believe in the race,” she cried. “It represents the survival of the
pushing.” “It has development.” “Decay fascinates me more.” “What of art?” she asked.
“It is a Mady Love?” “An illusion.”
“Religion?” “The fashionable substitute for belief.” “You are a skeptic Never
skepticism is the beginning of faith.” “What are you?” “To define is to
limit.” “Give me a clue.” “Threads snap. You would lose your way in the labyrinth.” “You
bewilder me. Let us talk of someone else.” “Our host is a delightful topic.
Years AO he was christened Prince Charming.” “Ah! don’t remind me of that,”
cried Dorian Gray. “Our host is rather horrid this evening,” answered the duchess
coloring I believe he thinks that Monmouth married me on purely scientific
principles as the best specimen he could find of a modern
butterfly.” “Well, I hope he won’t stick pins into you, Duchess,” laughed Doran Oh!
my maid does that already, Mr. Gray, when she's annoyed with me.” “And what does she
get annoyed with you about, Duchess?” “For the most trivial things, Mr.
Gray, I assure you. Usually because I come in at 10 minutes to 9 and tell her that
I must be dressed by half 8 How unreasonable of her! You should
give her warning.” “I don't Mr. Gray. Why, she invents hats for me. You remember the one
I wore at Lady Hilton's Garden Party You don’t, but it is nice of you to pretend
that you do. Well, she made it out of nothing. All good hats are made out of
nothing.” “Like all good reputations gladice interrupted Lord Henry. “Every
effect that one produces gives one an enemy. To be popular one must be a
mediocrity.” “Not with women,” said the duchess, shaking her head; “and women rule
the world. I assure you we can’t bear mediocrities. We women, as someone says,
love with our ears, just as you men love with your eyes, if you ever love at
all.” “It seems to me that we never do anything else,” murmured Dorian. “Ah! then,
you never really love, Mr. Gray,” answered the duchess with mock
sadness. “My dear Gladis cried Lord Henry.
“How can you say that? Romance lives by repetition, and repetition converts an
appetite into an art. Besides, each time that one loves is the only time one has
ever loved. Difference of object does not alter singleness of passion. It merely
intenses if I it. We can have in life but one great experience at best, and the
secret of life is to reproduce that experience as often as
possible.” “Even when one has been wounded by it, Harry?” asked the duchess after a
pause. “Especially when one has been wounded by it,” answered Lord Henry. The
duess turned and looked at Dorian Gray with a curious expression in her
eyes. “What do you say to that, Mr. Gray?” she inquired. Dorian hesitated for a moment.
Then he threw his head back and laughed.
“I always agree with Harry, Duchess.” “Even when he's wrong?” “Harry is never wrong,
Duchess.” “And does his philosophy make you happy?” “I have never searched for
happiness. Who wants happiness? I have searched for pleasure.” “And found it, Mr. Gray off
Too often.” The duchess sighed I'm searching for peace,” she said, “and if I
don’t go and dress, I shall have none this evening.” “Let me get you some orchids,
Duchess,” cried Dorian, starting to his feet and walking down the
conservatory. “You are flirting disgracefully with him,” said Lord Henry
to his cousin. “You had better take care.
He is very fascinating.” “If he were not, there would be no battle.”
“Greek meets Greek, then I'm on the side of the Trojans. They fought for a woman.” “They were
defeated.” “There are worse things than capture,” she answered. “You gallop with a loose
rain Pace gives life,” was the repost I shall write it in my diary
tonight What?” “That a burnt child loves the fire.” “I am not even singed. My wings
are untouched.” “You use them for everything, except accept
flight.” “Courage has passed from men to women. It is a new experience for us.” “You have a
rival.” “Who?” He laughed. “Lady narbar he whispered. “She perfectly adores
him.” “You fill me with apprehension. The appeal to antiquity is fatal to us who are
romanticists.” “Romanticists! You have all the methods of
science.” “Men have educated us.” “But not explained you.” “Describe us as a sex,” was her
challenge. “Sphinxes without secrets.” She looked at him,
smiling. “How long Mr. Gray is!” she said. “Let
us go and help him I've not yet told him
the color of my frock.” “Ah! you must suit your frock to his flowers Gladis That
would be a premature surrender.” “Romantic art begins with its
climax.” “I must keep an opportunity for retreat.” “In the paean manner?” “They found
safety in the desert. I could not do that.” “Women are not always allowed a
choice,” he answered, but hardly had he finished the sentence before from the
far end of the conservatory came a stifled groan, followed by the dull sound of a heavy
fall. Everybody started up. The duchess stood motionless in horror. And with fear
in his eyes, Lord Henry rushed through the flapping palms to find Dorian Gray
lying face downwards on the tiled floor in a deathlike swoon. He was carried at
once into the blue drawing room and laid upon one of the
sofas. After a short time, he came to himself and looked around with a dazed
expression. “What has happened?” he asked. “Oh!
I remember. Am I safe here, Harry?” He began to tremble. “My dear Dorian,” answered Lord
Henry, “you merely fainted. That was all.
You must have over tired yourself you'd better not come down to dinner. I will take your
place.” “No, I will come down,” he said, struggling to his feet. “I would rather
come down. I must not be alone.” He went to his room and
dressed. There was a wild recklessness of gayety in his manner as he sat at table,
but now and then a thrill of terror ran through him when he remembered that,
pressed against the window of the conservatory, like a white handkerchief,
he had seen the face of James vain watching him. CHAPTER